Finding Aid for Center for the Education of Women (University of Michigan) Records, 1919-[ongoing]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Individual Staff Files 1919-1999
  - Dorothy McGuigan 1919-1980
    - Research on Women Conference and Book Correspondence 1973-1975 (Box 34)
    - The Role of Women in Conflict and Peace 1975-1976 (Box 34)
    - A Sampler of Women's Studies, 1972-1973 (Box 34)
    - Rusty Schumacher (Interviews and Book Summaries) 1966-1970 (Box 34)
    - Rusty Schumacher (Women and Public Schools) undated (Box 34)
    - Sex Discrimination at UM (US Dept. of Health, Education, and Welfare Suit) 1970-1972 (Box 34)
    - Singles and Single Heads of Households 1973-1976 (Box 34)
    - Speeches and CEW Progress Reports undated (Box 34)
    - Status of Women at UM 1970-1979 (Box 34)
    - Student Wives 1969-1970 (Box 34)
    - Women in Higher Education Panel Papers undated (Box 34)
    - Women in Perspective Lecture Series
      - Alice Rossi, 10-19-1971 (Box 34)
      - Natalie Zemon Davis, 11-17-1971 (Box 34)
      - Marjorie Lansing, 12-7-1971 (Box 34)
      - Nancie Gonzalez, 1-24-1972 (Box 34)
      - Elizabeth Hardwick, 2-15-1972 (Box 34)
      - Selma Jean Cohen, 3-1-1972 (Box 34)
      - Gerda Lerner, 3-16-1972 (Box 34)
      - Sheila Tobias, 4-6-1972 (Box 34)
    - Women on Campus Symposium 1970 (Box 34)
    - Women's Caucuses and Organizations at UM 1972-1973 (Box 34)
    - "Women's Life Cycle and Public Policy: Research Conference V", November 7-8th 1979 (Box 34)
    - Women's Research Club Survey 1970 (Box 34)
    - "Women's Role in the Pre-Industrial Family in Europe", April 19-20th 1974 (Box 34)
    - Women's Studies Program 1971-1979, undated, 9 folders (Box 34)
    - Women's Studies Program Review 1979-1980 (Box 34)
  - Vivian Rogers 1984-1987
    Director Vivian Rogers' files, 1985-1987, document key issues during the brief time she served as CEW Director before health difficulties forced her to step down.
    - Affirmative Action Office 1986 (Box 35)
    - Black Women In Transition (Papers) 1986 (Box 35)
    - Computer Committee/Task Force 1985-1986 (Box 35)
    - Conferences, Meetings, and Workshops 1985-1987 (Box 35)
    - Correspondence 1985-1987 (Box 35)
    - Counseling Procedures and Issues 1984-1986 (Box 35)
    - Fundraising 1986 (Box 35)
    - Instructional Design undated (Box 35)
    - Internships 1985-1986 (Box 35)
      (Including WIS, International Women's Programs, etc.)
    - Lumpectomy Support Group 1987 (Box 35)
    - Miscellaneous 1986, undated (Box 35)
    - Non-Traditional Students 1985-1987 (Box 35)
    - Organizations Supporting Women 1985-1986 (Box 35)
    - Participant Files Policies 1985 (Box 35)
    - Program Ideas 1985 (Box 35)
    - Reports 1985-1986 (Box 35)
    - Scholarships 1985-1987 (Box 35)
    - Security 1985 (Box 35)
    - Supervision 1986 (Box 35)
    - Mary Ann Swain 1985-1986 (Box 35)
    - Visiting Scholars 1985-1987 (Box 35)
      (Janet Giele and Deb Umberson)
    - WING Women's Center Task Force 1987 (Box 35)
  - Patricia Wulp 1965-1995
    The files of associate director Patricia Wulp, 1968-1994, include extensive information about the programs sponsored by CEW, including the continuations of the chronological sets of 'Evening Program' and 'Programs' files (the beginning of which are located in the Topical Files). A study of these files reveals many of the ways in which CEW has and continues to support women and education over Wulp's tenure of nearly thirty years. Many files include detailed planning information and notes kept by Wulp throughout the planning process.
    - Administration 1976-1981 (Box 35)
    - Administration Binder 1972-1974, 2 folders (Box 35)
      (Started during tenure as CEW Acting Director during Jean Campbell sabbatical)
    - Administrative Internship Program 1987-1990 (Box 35)
    - Ageism 1972-1974 (Box 35)
    - American Association of University Women Scholarship 1991-1992 (Box 35)
    - Anxiety Workshop, Winter 1991 (Box 35)
    - Arrow 1972-1973 (Box 35)
    - Beyond the Classroom, October 25th 1972 (Box 35)
    - Jean Campbell Nomination 1971 (Box 35)
    - Career Decision Making Workshops (The Step Before the Job Search) 1979-1981, 1990-1993, 8 folders (Box 35)
      (Various group facilitators reporting to Pat Wulp; includes papers from M. Fabian, B. Anton, Lineve McKie, and others)
    - Career Strategies Workshop, Winter 1991 (Box 35)
    - Challenge for Women 1993 (Box 35)
    - Communication Skills in the Workplace, Classroom, and Home, Fall 1992 (Box 35)
    - Connections to the World of Work, Spring 1991 (Box 35)
    - Conversation with Couples, April 4th 1974 (Box 35)
    - Conversations at the Center
      - The Child and the Working Mother 1971-1972 (Box 35)
      - The Marketplace for the Educated Woman 1971 (Box 35)
    - Coping with Reentry 1975 (Box 35)
    - Counseling Procedures 1975-1980 (Box 35)
    - Day on Campus, May 17th 1978 (Box 36)
      (Re-Entry orientation for returning women)
    - Discussions and Ideas 1972-1973 (Box 36)
    - Effective Assertiveness 1992 (Box 36)
    - Evening Program 1982-1985, 1989-1995, 14 folders (Box 36)
    - Explosion of Research on Women's Health, Winter 1992 (Box 36)
    - Fees 1982, 1993 (Box 36)
    - Financial Assistance Correspondence 1992-1993 (Box 36)
    - Gearing Up for Graduate and Professional School Exams 1976-1978 (Box 36)
    - Getting or Starting a Job Series
      - General 1977-1978 (Box 36)
      - Starting Your Own Business, 11/1/1977 (Box 36)
      - Money Jobs, 12/6/1977 (Box 36)
      - Administrative Skills at Work 2/7/1978 (Box 36)
      - Real Estate and Property Management 3/7/1978 (Box 36)
      - Computer Jobs, 12/9/1978 (Box 36)
      - Professional Jobs 2/13/1979 (Box 36)
      - Women in Non-Traditional Jobs 4/10/1979 (Box 36)
    - Graduate/Professional Programs 1982-1983 (Box 36)
    - GRE, GMAT, & LSAT: Getting Ready 1990 (Box 36)
    - In the Know 1989-1991, 3 folders (Box 36)
    - Internships 1977-1985 (Box 36)
    - Juggling Act 1989 (Box 36)
    - King/Chavez/Parks Scholars
      - Florence Bonner, Winter 1990 (Box 36)
      - Susan Frazier-Kouassi, Fall 1990 (Box 36)
      - Denise Chavez, Fall 1991 (Box 36)
    - Lunchtime Conversation 1973-1974 (Box 36)
    - MAWDAC 1988-1989 (Box 36)
    - Mid-Career Focus Groups 1991-1992 (Box 36)
    - Miscellaneous 1972-1976 (Box 36)
    - Jo Ann Morgan 1989 (Box 36)
    - NAWDAC Continuing Education for Women Committee 1970-1972 (Box 36)
    - New Research on Women, March 15th 1973 (Box 36)
    - New Research on Women II, March 19th 1975 (Box 36)
    - Not Losing Her Memory 1991-1992 (Box 36)
    - Office of the 90s 1989 (Box 36)
    - Participant Counseling Form Revisions and Coding 1965-1966, 1976 (Box 36)
      (Helen Hornbeck Tanner Papers)
    - Personal Empowerment, Winter 1992 (Box 37)
    - Press Releases 1985-1990, 6 folders (Box 37)
    - Preview the Future 1971 (Box 37)
    - Programs and Projects 1969-1970 (Box 37)
    - Programs by Academic Year 1970/71-1987/88, 23 folders (Box 37)
    - Programs by Academic Year 1988/89-1991/92, 7 folders (Box 38)
    - Reports from Returning Women: Research and Progress 1975-1977 (Box 38)
    - Research in Action Symposium 1991 (Box 38)
    - Research on Women seminar group 1969 (Box 38)
    - Singles and Single Heads of Households 1973-1974 (Box 38)
    - Securing Your Future (Graduate School from a Woman's Perspective) 1989 (Box 38)
    - Securing Your Future (The Graduate Experience from a Woman's Perspective) 1990, 2 folders (Box 38)
      (includes photographs)
    - Securing Your Future (Graduate School from a Woman's Perspective) 1991-1992, 3 folders (Box 38)
    - Social Work Project 1983 (Box 38)
    - Speeches, Conferences, etc. 1968-1977 (Box 38)
    - Staff Racism Workshop 1987-1988 (Box 38)
    - Stress Management, Fall 1993 (Box 38)
    - Tenth Anniversary Luncheon, September 19th (Box 38)
    - Twenty-Fifth Anniversary Conference 1989-1990, 2 folders (Box 38)
    - University of Michigan Departments 1976-1981 (Box 38)
    - University of Michigan Resources 1973-1980 (Box 38)
    - Georgia Watermulder Papers 1965-1968 (Box 38)
    - Women and the Workplace 1986 (Box 38)
    - Women in Graduate Education 1972 (Box 38)
      (includes material from the Committee on the Status of Women in Graduate Education)
    - Women on Campus 1970 (Box 38)
    - Women's Financial Information Workshop, Spring 1991 (Box 38)
    - Women's Life Cycle and Public Policy Research Conference 1979 (Box 38)
    - Women's Lives in the Information Society-March 9th 1985, 1984-1985 (Box 38)
    - Women's Resource Center (Grand Rapids)
      - Board Affairs and Correspondence 1973-1977, 2 folders (Box 38)
      - Board Meetings 1975-1976, 1980, 3 folders (Box 39)
        (includes bylaws and articles of incorporation)
      - College Liaison Committee 1973-1980 (Box 39)
      - University of Michigan/CEW involvement 1973-1974 (Box 39)
    - Admissions Referrals 1967-1984 (Box 43)
    - Social Work Interns 1974-1977, 1982-1985 (Box 43)
- Audiovisual Materials 1963-1997
  The Audio-Visual Material series consists of many CEW awards programs, lectures, and information material. The video materials include two video reel-to-reel trigger tapes, "The Perils of Paula" and the "Street Corner Society", meant to spark group discussions and a videotape (U-matic format) of the Center's "Two Women, Twenty Years," which details the life stories of two non-traditional students who were involved with CEW when they received their education at the University of Michigan. Other highlights include several VHS recordings of CEW Scholarship Awards programs, the Elizabeth Mullin-Welch lecture series, videos on the Women of Color in the Academy Project, an informational video describing the programs and services at CEW, and an informational video about the CEW sponsored Science for Life program. The audio materials are stronger for the 1970s, including several talks from the 1975-1976 Brownbag series (aka Research Reports from Returning Women), as well as several discussion groups, conferences, and symposia. There are also audio recordings of various CEW programs from the 1980s and 1990s.
  - Videocassettes (3/4")
    - Center for the Education of Women (Informational) 1992 (14 minutes) (Box 40)
    - "Two Women, Twenty Years" ca 1970 (Box 40)
  - Videocassettes (VHS)
    - Center for the Education of Women (Informational) 1992 (14 minutes) (Box 40)
    - CEW 30th Anniversary Conference "Women Transforming Higher Education" (James Duderstadt and Dr. Paula Brownlee, speakers), ca 1994 (Box 40)
    - CEW Scholarship Awards undated (Box 40)
    - CEW Scholarship Awards April 19, 1994 (Box 40)
    - CEW Scholarship Awards 1997 (Box 40)
    - Elizabeth Mullin-Welch Lecture (Terry Savage speaker) undated (Box 40)
    - Elizabeth Mullin-Welch Lecture (Sharon McCrane speaker) 1994 (Box 40)
    - "Science for Life: Do it for Yourself!" 1993 13:55 (Box 40)
    - Women of Color in the Academy Project undated (Box 40)
    - Women of Color in the Academy Project, Liberating Fears (Dr. Carolyn Meyers) 1997 46 minutes (Box 40)
  - Video reels
    - "Perils of Paula", undated, 25:45 (Box 40)
    - "The Street Corner Society" undated (Box 40)
  - Audiocassettes
    - Elizabeth Mullin-Welch Lecture (Charlotte Bunch speaker) 1997 (Box 40)
    - Women's Health Panel on Women's Health Research 1992 (Box 40)
    - "Women's Lives: Breaking the Barriers" 1992, 2 audiocassettes (Box 40)
    - Michigan Agenda for Women Town Meeting (James Duderstadt and graduate women) 1995 (Box 40)
    - CEW Discussion (committee to involve women in University publicity and fundraising) undated (Box 40)
    - Working Women Seminar undated, 2 audiocassettes (Box 40)
    - Jean Campbell Lecture (Robin Wright speaker) 1990 (Box 40)
    - Girls into Science and Technology (Dr. Allison Kelly speaker) 1985 (Box 40)
    - "Realities of the Workplace" 1981 (Box 40)
    - Gender and Custody 1995 (Box 40)
    - Roundtable Discussion undated (Box 40)
    - Beyond the Classroom: Alternative Careers for Teachers 10/25/1972 (Box 41)
    - Women and Retail Credit roundtable discussion, JC Penney Educational & Consumer Relations Department, Fall/Winter 1973 (Box 41)
    - Working Woman Student (1/24/1974) and Conversations with Couples I 4/4/1974 (Box 41)
    - Conversations with Couples II 4/4/1974 (Box 41)
    - Women's Roles Conference
      - Power Structure 3/15/1974 (Box 41)
      - Peasant Society 3/15/1974 (Box 41)
      - Transition to Urban Society 3/16/1974 (Box 41)
      - Anthro-History 3/16/1974 (Box 41)
      - End of Discussion, summary 3/16/1974 (Box 41)
      - Final Session 3/16/1974 (Box 41)
    - Young Mothers (Sessions I-III) June 1974 (3 tapes) (Box 41)
    - Brownbags (Research Reports from Returning Women)
      - Alice Smuts 9/30/1975 (Box 41)
      - M. Wright, "Self Concept and Coping Mechanisms of Black Women Students in a Predominantly White University" 10/14/1975 (Box 41)
      - Dean Falk, "Neuroanatomy of old World Monkeys and how this Relates to Human Evolution" 10/28/1975 (Box 41)
      - Martha Olmstead 11/11/1975 (Box 41)
      - Christine Allen, "Effect of Transcendental Meditation and EMC Bio-Feedback on Relazation [sic] and Stuttering 11/24/1975 or 11/26/1975 (Box 41)
      - Bowker, Joan "Crisis Coping the First Three Months of Pregnancy", 12/9/1975 (Box 41)
      - Sue Golden, "Pre-School Families and Work" 1/20/1976 (Box 41)
      - Marsha Clinkscales, "Differences of Non-verbal Behaviour Between Blacks and Whites" 2/3/1976 (Box 41)
      - Prudence Brown, "Women Coping with Divorce" 2/17/1976 (Box 41)
      - Sandra McAffee, "Educational Innovations in Black Colleges" 3/2/1976 (Box 41)
      - Cheryl Reichert, "The Immunological Approach to Cancer Research" 3/16/1976 (Box 41)
      - Victoria Binion, "Role and Status of Black Women in Black Families" 4/6/1976 (Box 41)
      - Dottie Martin, "Medieval Literature in Islamic Settings" 4/20/1976 (Box 41)
      - Barbara Gutek, "Women in Non-Traditional Occupations" 5/18/1976 (Box 41)
      - Cecilia Dreyfuss, "Changes in Women's Lives as Reflected in Drama from Aeschylus to Goethe" 6/1/1976 (Box 41)
    - Unspecified conference/symposium, (work order # 6595) 1976
      - Tape 1: "Women in Non-Traditional Roles Panel" 1/27/1976 (Box 41)
      - Tape 2: "Matching Women in Careers" (Box 41)
      - Tape 3: "Problems and Rewards" (Box 41)
    - "Role of Women in Conflict and Peace" Symposium 3/24/1976, 2 tapes (Box 41)
    - "Problems of Women's Continuing Education" Research Symposium 3/1/1977, 2 audiocassettes (Box 41)
    - Conference Session 19: "Life Stages and Learning Interests" (American Association for Higher Education's 33rd National Conference on Higher Education) March 19-22, 1978 (Box 41)
    - WUOM/Roger Sutton Featuring Jean Campbell December 1980 (20 minutes) (Box 41)
    - J. Dodson "Black Women and Family" (side 1) and STEP Program (side 2) undated (Box 41)
    - "Janet's tapes on supervision of interns" undated, 2 audiocassettes (Box 41)
    - "Name of the Game" undated (Box 41)
    - "1954 film 195 feet copy 1 Panel Discussion on Career and Family with a UM Senior particip." undated (Box 41)
    - "Sarah" (About Returning to School) undated (6-7 minutes) (Box 41)
    - 'Sarah' (Stimulus for Dearborn) undated (Box 41)
    - Unspecified Conference/Symposium (work order 7637) undated
      - Keynote Address, Patricia Bell Scott (54:40) (Box 41)
      - Panel: Job Market Info, Farmer/Gray/Wright/Jones/Butts (75:00) (Box 41)
      - Equal Opportunity in the Workplace, P. Robinson (76:30) (Box 41)
      - Career Decision Making, G. Parker / M. Emerson (63:20) (Box 41)
      - Job and Career Transitions, J. Washington (68:07) (Box 41)
      - General Session, Dixon/Jones (62:00) (Box 41)
    - Women and Public Policy Conference undated (Box 41)
  - Audio reels (7-inch)
    - Louise Cain moderating WUOM broadcast on Continuing Education for Women, [1963, 1964?], Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
      - [Part 1], [8740-SR-1-1]; mp3 file; (Louise Cain; Gretchen Groth; Hope Davis; Deborah Friedman; Helen Tanner; Radio panel discussing contemporary women's issues.)
        [Digitized audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.]
    - Women's Continuing Education Conference 3/30/1967 (Box 41)
    - Unidentified program 4/6/1967 (Box 41)
    - Women in Action Conference-Workshop 3/26/1969, 2 reels (Box 41)
    - Unlabeled undated, 2 reels (Box 41)
  - Audio reels (5-inch)
    - Women on Campus Symposium (set 1) 10/14/1970, 4 reels (Box 41)
    - Women on Campus Symposium (set 2) 10/14/1970, 6 reels (Box 41)
  - Other
    - Printed Program for Women in Action Conference-Workshop 3/26/1969 (Box 41)